曾有一世界
Once there was a world
它c我的星球]什N不同
not so very different from our own.
偶有些自然暮或者是大模的火山爆l
There were occasional natural catastrophes, massive volcanic eruptions
r不r有小行星降R在星球上砸坑
and, every once in a while, an asteroid would come barreling out of the blue to do some damage.
可在最初的100f年Y
But for the first billion years or so,
它很像是一天堂
it would've seemed like a paradise.
@大概就是金星在太系年pr的幼
This is what we think the planet Venus might have looked like when our solar system was young.
然後 一切就_始得糟糕了
Then things started to go horribly wrong.
宇宙大探索
第十二集
金星或S曾是一天堂
The planet Venus, which once may have seemed like a heaven,
但F在s是一地z
turned into a kind of hell.
造成@差的原因是因橛幸恍┪⒚畹淖匀黄胶獗淮蚱屏
The difference between the two can be a delicate balance,
而且是比你想像中更槲⒚畹年PS
far more delicate than you might imagine.
@平衡一旦被打破 就再也o法挽回
Once things began to unravel, there was no way back.
@就是金星
This is what Venus,
距x我最近的行星 今天看上去的幼
our nearest planetary neighbor, looks like today.
金星上的海洋已消失很久了
Venus's oceans are long gone.
星球的表面F在比烤t要C
The surface is hotter than a broiling oven,
岬米阋匀诨U
hot enough to melt lead.
槭颤N呢
Why?
你也SJ檫@是因榻鹦堑教的距x要比地球少30%
You might think it's because Venus is 30% closer to the Sun than the Earth is,
但@不是真正的原因
but that's not the reason.
金星F在完全被硫酸覆w著
Venus is completely covered by clouds of sulfuric acid
缀]有光可以照射到它的表面
that keep almost all the sunlight from reaching the surface.
按理碚f@金星比地球更寒冷
That ought to make Venus much colder than the Earth.
但楹谓鹦如此的灼幔
So why is Venus scorching hot?
那是因橛行〔糠值年光
It's because the small amount of sunlight
穿^拥诌_了地面
that trickles in through the clouds to reach the surface
s]能反射回去
can't get back out again.
能量不能散l是由於饷艿拇庾韪
The flow of energy is blocked by a dense atmosphere
那就是二氧化碳
of carbon dioxide.
二氧化碳QCO2
That carbon dioxide gas-- or CO2 for short--
它就像毯子一幼柚崃康纳l
acts like a smothering blanket to keep the heat in.
]人在金星上煤
No one is burning coal
或是_著大R力的汽在上面逛
or driving big gas-guzzlers on Venus.
自然能绲舡h境的平衡
Nature can destroy an environment
而不需要借助人的力量
without any help from intelligent life.
金星F在正於烈的厥倚中
Venus is in the grip of a runaway greenhouse effect.
槭颤N我F在像是在一碗Y？
Why does it look like we're inside a bowl?
那是因饷艿拇毫
It's due to the intense atmospheric pressure.
@是金星13的骸
That's the wreck of Venera 13.
1982年
In 1982, the scientists and engineers
K的科W家c工程
of what was then the Soviet Union
成功地⑦@艘探y器送到了金星
successfully landed this spacecraft on Venus.
他O法w船
They managed to keep it refrigerated
保持了2小r以上的冷B
for overtwo hours,
它能o四周拍照
so it could photograph its surroundings...
K⒄掌骰亓说厍
and transmit the images back to Earth
S後w船上的子O渚S了
before the on-board electronics were fried.
金星c地球在Q生初期具有相同的
Venus and Earth started out with about the same amount
碳含量 但星球s被推上了
of carbon, but the two worlds were propelled
截然不同的l展道路
along radically different paths,
碳元素在其中起到了Q定性的作用
and carbon was the decisive element in both stories.
在金星 缀跛有的大
On Venus, it's almost all in the form of gas--
都由二氧化碳M成
carbon dioxide-- in the atmosphere.
地球上大部分的碳已在久h的年代中
Most of the carbon on Earth has been stored for eons
以碳酸}r的形式被Υ嫫
in solid vaults of carbonate rock,
就像@一K 它就是其中一N形式
like this one, part of a chain that forms
@就是著名的多佛海岸白色已
the celebrated White Cliffs of Dover,
它位於英吉利海right on the English Channel.
是哪位巨人修建了@拥氖澜缙嬗^？
What titan built this wonder of the world?
那是一N比^要小1000倍的生物
A creature a thousand times smaller than a pinhead.
狄匀f|
Trillions of them.
它叫渭胞藻
One-celled algae.
火山⒍氧化碳送入大忉
Volcanoes supply carbon dioxide to the atmosphere,
海洋⑺慢地吸收
and the oceans slowly absorb it.
@^程要延m好装偃f年
Working over the course of millions of years,
先是微小的藻吸收了二氧化碳
the microscopic algae harvested the carbon dioxide
K⑺D化檫@些小
and turned it into these tiny shells.
日e月累 最K沉e榘
They accumulated in thick deposits of chalk,
我也Q之槭灰岩 它e聚在海床上
or limestone, on the ocean floor.
最K 永不停息的地み\⒑４餐破
Later, the restless Earth pushed up the sea floor
⑺塑造成@些巨大的已
and carved out these massive cliffs.
其他的海洋生物
Other marine creatures
用二氧化碳建造了巨大的珊瑚礁
took in carbon dioxide to build enormous coral reefs.
海洋也可以把溶解的二氧化碳DQ槭灰岩
And the oceans converted dissolved CO2 into limestone
而不需要生物的椭
even without any help from life.
最K 只有微量的二氧化碳怏w
As a result, only a trace amount was left as a gas
留在了地球的大庵
in Earth's atmosphere.
不到每百分之一中的三百分之一
Not even three-hundredths of one percent.
相於每1f分子中
Think of it-- fewer than three molecules
只有不到3分子保留下
out of every ten thousand.
而@分子就是最PI的因素
And yet, it makes the critical difference
Q定了地球是生命的吠吝是荒之地
between a barren wasteland and a garden of life on Earth.
要是一c二氧化碳都]有
With no CO2 at all,
地球被冰
the Earth would be frozen.
可要是二氧化碳的盗吭俣嘁槐
And with twice as many,
也就是像前面所f的 每1f分子中
we're still talking about only six molecules
有6分子保留下
out of ten thousand.
令人不安的炎峋u
Things would get uncomfortably hot
o人硪幌盗械}
and cause us some serious problems...
不^不像金星那N 一c都不
but never as hot as Venus; not even close.
在好装偃f年前
That planet lost its ocean to space
@行星上的海洋就已消失到太空中了
billions of years ago.
]有了海洋 它就]有k法目庵
Without an ocean, it had no way to capture CO2
捕@二氧化碳 K⑺存榈V物|
from the atmosphere and store it as a mineral.
l的火山中a生的二氧化碳
The CO2 from erupting volcanoes
不嗟胤e累
just continued to build up.
r至今日 金星上的大庖比地球重90倍
Today, that atmosphere is 90 times heavier than ours.
缀跞部由灼岬亩氧化碳怏wM成
Almost all of it is heat-trapping carbon dioxide.
@就是槭颤N金星成如此酷的地z
That's why Venus is such a ferocious inferno
生命o法在此扎根的原因
so hostile to life.
地球t恰恰c此相反
The Earth, in stunning contrast,
它是有生命的星球
is alive.
它呼吸
It breathes...
不^很慢
but very slowly.
1年才能完成1次呼吸
A single breath takes a whole year.
森林Y包含了地球上大部分的生命
The forests contain most of Earth's life,
大部分的森林都位於北半球
and most forests are in the Northern Hemisphere.
北半球的春季到
When spring comes to the north,
森林吸入空庵械亩氧化碳
the forests inhale carbon dioxide from the air
KS之生L ⒋蟮劁MG色
and grow, turning the land green.
大庵械亩氧化碳含量S之下降
The amount of CO2 in the atmosphere goes down.
秋天降R 植物落~ S之枯萎
When fall comes and the plants drop their leaves, they decay,
⒍氧化碳呼出到大庵
exhaling the carbon dioxide back into the atmosphere.
同拥倪^程也l生在南半球
The same thing happens in the Southern Hemisphere
只是季是相反的
at the opposite time of the year.
但南半球大部分是海洋
But the Southern Hemisphere is mostly ocean.
因此 是北半球的森林
So it's the forests of the north
控制了全球每年二氧化碳含量的化
that control the annual changes in the global CO2.
地球已像@雍粑了
The Earth has been breathing like this
登f年
for tens of millions of years.
]有人注意到@一c 直到1958年
But nobody noticed until 1958,
有一位海洋W家叫查斯?戴S?基林
when an oceanographer named Charles David Keeling
他O了一N方法 可以精_地y量
devised a way to accurately measure
空庵卸氧化碳的含量
the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.
基林lF了地球的微呼吸
Keeling discovered the Earth's exquisite respiration.
但他也lF了一些令人震@的事
But he also discovered something shocking--
有一底衷谝匀祟v史上前所未有的速度上升
a rapid rise, unprecedented in human history,
那就是空庵卸氧化碳的整w水平
in the overall level of CO2,
至今@化一直在^m
one that has continued ever since.
二氧化碳水平的@人化
It's a striking departure from the CO2 levels that prevailed
始於rIc文明的d起r期
during the rise of agriculture and civilization.
H上
In fact, the Earth has seen nothing like it
地球在^去的300f年不是@幼
for three million years.
我楹稳绱舜_信
How can we be so sure?
C就在水Y
The evidence is written in water.
地球保存著一份的日
The Earth keeps a detailed diary
它就在^去下的雪Y
written in the snows of yesteryear.
夂蚩W家出冰芯
Climate scientists have drilled ice cores
母窳痔mu和南O洲的冰川深
from the depths of glaciers in Greenland and Antarctica.
h古的空獗焕г诹吮友Y
The ice layers have ancient air trapped inside them.
我可以x到地球大獾耐暾
We can read the unbroken record of Earth's atmosphere
一直可以追溯到8f年前
that extends back over the last 800,000 years.
在以往的所有rg
In all that time,
大庵械亩氧化碳抵]有超^
the amount of carbon dioxide in the air never rose
每百分之一的空庵泻有三百分之一的二氧化碳
above three-hundredths of one percent.
但到了二十世o
That is, until the turn of the 20th century.
它就_始定而迅速的上升K保持至今
And it's been going up steadily and rapidly ever since.
F在@抵
It's now more than 40% higher
已比工I革命前高出了40%
than before the Industrial Revolution.
通^燃煤 石油和煤
By burning coal, oil and gas,
人文明在放出二氧化碳
our civilization is exhaling carbon dioxide
hh超^了地球所能吸收的速度
much faster than Earth can absorb it.
因此大庵械亩氧化碳在不喾e累
So CO2 is building up in the atmosphere.
@星球在升
The planet is heating up.
每一l岬奈矬w都能射出某N我肉眼看不的光
Every warm object radiates a kind of light we can't see with the naked eye--
那就是峒t外
thermal infrared light.
即使在黑暗中 我的身w也能散l出不可的彷射
We all glow with invisible heat radiation, even in the dark.
如果用t外^察地球 它就是@幼
This is what the Earth looks like in the infrared.
你看到的是行星本身的l
You're seeing the planet's own body heat.
光照射到地面
Incoming light from the Sun hits the surface.
地球本身吸收大部分的能量
The Earth absorbs much of that energy,
地球升
which heats the planet up
亩地表l出t外
and makes the surface glow in infrared light.
但空庵械亩氧化碳
But the carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
又吸收散l出的大部分崃
absorbs most of that outgoing heat radiation,
把@些崃康拇蟛糠钟骰氐孛
sending much of it right back to the surface.
地球得更
This makes the planet even warmer.
@就是所^的厥倚
That's all there is to the greenhouse effect.
它的基本物理原理
It's basic physics,
就在於把流拥哪芰勘４嫦
just bookkeeping of the energy flow.
P於它]什N好h的
There's nothing controversial about it.
如果大庵幸稽c二氧化碳都]有
If we didn't have any carbon dioxide in our atmosphere,
地球就成一大雪球
the Earth would just be a great big snowball,
人也就不存在
and we wouldn't be here.
因此 p度的厥倚是件好事
So, a little greenhouse effect is a good thing.
可它要是大 就造成夂虻牟环定
But a big one can destabilize the climate
甚至У羧祟的生存方式
and wreck our way of life.
好吧 但我怎N知道人是}的根源？
All right... but how do we know that we're the problem?
也S是地球本身е露氧化碳的增加
Maybe the Earth itself is causing the rise in CO2.
也S和煤c石油的燃oP
Maybe it has nothing to do with the coal and oil we burn.
或S是那些死的火山
Maybe it's those damn volcanoes.
每隔啄 西西里u的埃特Every few years, Mount Etna, in Sicily, blows its stack.
每次的大模l都把装偃f二氧化碳
Each big eruption sends millions of tons of CO2
送入空
into the atmosphere.
如果我把
Now, combine that with the output
地球上所有的火山l合起淼脑
of all the other volcanic activity on the planet.
我按最大盗窟M行科WAy
Let's take the largest scientific estimate--
每年大概有5|二氧化碳
about 500 million tons of volcanic CO2
被送入空庵
entering the atmosphere ever year.
上去很多 ΣΓ
Sounds like a lot, right?
可@抵颠不到人每年a生的二氧化碳盗康2%
But that's not even two percent of the 30 billion tons of CO2
那就是1年300|
that our civilization is cranking out every year.
而且 有很有趣的F象
And, funny thing,
大庵卸氧化碳的增加量
the measured increase in CO2 in the atmosphere
c我所知的 即是通^燃煤 石油和煤猱a生的二氧化碳
tallies with the known amount we're dumping there
好相同
by burning coal, oil and gas.
火山a生的二氧化碳有一明@的特徵
Volcanic CO2 has a distinct signature--
c化石燃料燃ra生的二氧化碳相比
it's slightly heavier than the kind produced
它要稍微重一些
by burning fossil fuels.
我可以分辨出@烧叩牟e
We can tell the difference between the two
通^λM行原子e的z
when we examine them at the atomic level.
zY果很明@C 空庵性黾拥亩氧化碳
It's clear that the increased CO2 in the air
不是碜曰鹕
is not from volcanoes.
更重要的是 夂蜃暖的程度c
What's more, the observed warming is as much as predicted
空庵卸氧化碳增加的程度差不多
from the measured increase in carbon dioxide.
@烧呔o密P
It's a pretty tight case.
人排放二氧化碳的C都在@上面
Our fingerprints are all over this one.
每年30|二氧化碳到底有多少?
How much is 30 billion tons of CO2 per year?
如果我把它撼梢固w
If you compressed it into solid form,
它的we就和
it would occupy about the same volume
多佛海岸的白色已虏畈欢
as the White Cliffs of Dover.
@就是我每年排放到空庵械亩氧化碳的盗
And we're adding that much CO2 to the air every year,
永o休止 年鸵荒
relentlessly, year after year.
很不幸的是
Unlucky for us, the main waste product
人文明a生的主要垃圾a品不是物|
of our civilization is not just any substance.
而是能θ球夂蛘It happens to be the chief climate-regulating gas
a匦Ч的毒 年年如此
of our global thermostat, year in, year out.
^多的二氧化碳就相於看不的毒
Too bad CO2 is an invisible gas.
如果我能看到它……
Maybe if we could see it...
如果我的眼睛能感到二氧化碳
If our eyes were sensitive to CO2--
也S在宇宙中有@拥纳物
and perhaps there are such beings in the cosmos--
如果我能看二氧化碳
if we could see all that carbon dioxide,
那就]有人能否定@一切
then we would overcome the denial
K充分t解到人Υ獾乐赜绊
and grasp the magnitude of our impact on the atmosphere.
但全球暖的C
But the evidence that the world is getting warmer
就在我身
is all around us.
首先我z查一下
For starters, let's just check the thermometers.
世界各地庀笳镜囟扔
Weather stations around the world
自1880年代起
have been keeping reliable temperature records
它一直保存著可靠的囟扔
since the 1880s,
美宇航局用@些u了一幅地D
and NASA has used the data to compile a map
地D涵w了所有的rg段
tracking the average temperatures
用作跟世界各地平均氐淖化
around the world through time.
S色意味著囟容^高
Yellow means warmer temperatures
高於1880年代任何地^的平均水平
than the average, for any region in the 1880s.
橙色意味著炎
Orange means hot.
t色意味著比炎岣
And red means hotter.
世界已得比19世o更嘏了
The world is warmer than it was in the 19th century.
那r 全球各地的厥怯惺芬碜罹衡的
Back then, at the greatest fair the world has ever seen,
一位被z忘的天才曾O想了一解Q}的方案
a forgotten genius demonstrated the solution to this problem.
跟我
Come with me.
曾有@右世界
Once there was a world
它不太嵋膊惶冷
that was not too hot and not too cold.
囟冗m中
It was just right.
然後有一天 @Y的人
Then there came a time when the life it sustained
_始注意到他可鄣牡厍蛟诎l生化
began to notice our lovely planet was changing.
@K不是f我]有A到它的到
And it's not as if we didn't see it coming.
早在1896年
As far back as 1896,
三十一. P於碳酸空庵Φ孛囟鹊挠绊
瑞典科W家斯凡特?阿尼斯
the Swedish scientist Svante Arrhenius
通^算lF 如果大庵械亩氧化碳含量再增加1倍
calculated that doubling the amount
大饩腿厥乙话
就能北O的冰融化
of CO2 in the atmosphere would melt the Arctic ice.
到了1930年代 美物理W家E.O.赫伯特
In the 1930s, the American physicist E. O. Hulburt,
在海室Y
at the Naval Research Laboratory,
_J了@Y果
confirmed that result.
二氧化碳令地球
到那r橹 @一切依然是理
So far, it was still just theoretical.
S後 英工程w?卡德
But then, the English engineer Guy Callendar
人榕欧哦氧化碳於氐挠绊
把@些CY合起 向人展示
assembled the evidence to show
二氧化碳含量c全球平均
that both the CO2 and the average global temperature
都在不嗌仙中
were actually increasing.
就算是F在 人也可能在o意中改了全球夂
Even now, man may be unwittingly changing the world's climate
通^文明a生的U物
through the waste products of his civilization.
由於人通^工Sc汽的排放
Due to our release, through factories
每年有超^
and automobiles every year, of more than
60|的二氧化碳a生
six billion tons of carbon dioxide,
空馕收了更多碜造短的崃
which helps air absorb heat from the Sun,
大庾得越碓
our atmosphere seems to be getting warmer.
@是不是件氖?
This is bad?
嗯 通^算表明
Well, it's been calculated, a few degrees rise
地球囟鹊妮p微升高
in the Earth's temperature
地球O的冰帽熔化
would melt the polar ice caps.
二氧化碳c夂
"前的理 假O了二氧化碳：
人的活尤绾斡绊未淼夂蚰兀"
1960年 卡?_根在他的博士文Y
In 1960,Carl Sagan's PhD thesis
第一次算了
included the first calculation
金星上失控的厥倚
of the runaway greenhouse effect on Venus.
@是他Id趣的一部分
This was part of a career-long interest
於行星大 包括我的星球的d趣
in the atmospheres of the planets, including our own.
夂蜃化:我正於地球暖的?
在1980u作的最初那部宇宙系列片中 卡?_根警告f
In the original Cosmos series, in 1980, Carl Sagan warned...
大庵性黾拥亩氧化碳夂虻挠绊
"我正在放大量的二氧化碳
We are releasing vast quantities of carbon dioxide,
加×厥倚
increasing the greenhouse effect.
用不了多久
It may not take much
地球的夂蚓失去平衡
to destabilize the Earth's climate,
把我在宇宙中@唯一的家@ 像天堂一拥牡胤
to convert this heaven, our only home in the cosmos,
槿碎g地z"
into a kind of hell.
卡f^@些之後
Since Carl spoke those words,
我在^m加重大獾呢
we've burdened the atmosphere of our world with an additional
每年又多增加了4千|二氧化碳的排放
400 billion tons of carbon dioxide.
如果我不改@F
If we don't change our ways,
我未淼暮⒆面σ什N拥男乔
what will the planet be like in our children's future?
根科W研究目的Y果
Based on scientific projections,
如果我^m保持著F有的模式不
if we just keep on doing business as usual,
我的子O面ζDU的未
our kids are in for a rough ride.
致命的崂 破o的乾旱
Killer heat waves, record droughts,
不嗌高的海平面 大模的物N缃^
rising sea levels, mass extinction of species.
我曾那叭耸种欣^承了一富的世界
We inherited a bountiful world
夂蛳Ψ定
made possible by a relatively stable climate.
rI繁s 文明d盛
Agriculture and civilization flourished
延m了千年之久
for thousands of years.
可F在 人的冷漠c婪把@一切推向了危U的境地
And now, our carelessness and greed put all of that at risk.
好吧 如果科W家有那N害
Okay, so if we scientists are so good
可以作出P於夂虻娜绱碎Lh的可怕Ay
at making these dire, long-term predictions about the climate,
那槭颤N就不能把天y准一c呢?
How come we're so lousy about predicting the weather?
有 今年我家l的冬天特e寒冷
Besides, this year, we had a colder winter in my town.
我的科W家知不知道
For all us scientists know,
f不定我F在面Φ氖侨球冷呢
we could be in for global cooling.
天夂夂蚴遣煌的概念
Here's the difference between weather and climate...
天庵傅氖嵌r期鹊拇庾化
Weather is what the atmosphere does in the short term--
可能是仔r 也可能是滋
hour to hour, day to day.
天馐亲化莫y的
Weather is chaotic, which means that even
@意味著即使是微小的干_也能引起大模的化
a microscopic disturbance can lead to large-scale changes.
@就是槭颤Nκ天後的天忸Ay是]有用的
That's why those ten-day weather forecasts are useless.
巴厘u上的一b蝴蝶扇恿顺岚 六周以後
A butterfly flaps its wings in Bali, and six weeks later,
你在因州的敉饣槎Y就被狂L暴雨У袅
your outdoor wedding in Maine is ruined.
夂蜓芯康t是Lr期的天獾钠骄化
Climate is the long-term average
跨越幅度有好啄
of the weather, over a number of years.
它是由@星球上能改大饽芰科胶獾牧αQ定的
It's shaped by global forces that alter the energy balance
比如f 光的化
in the atmosphere, such as changes in the Sun,
地球自DS的A斜度
the tilt of the Earth's axis,
地球反射回太空的日照量
the amount of sunlight the Earth reflects back to space
空庵械厥怏w舛
and the concentration of greenhouse gases in the air.
它中任何一的化都能影夂
A change in any of them affects the climate
而且它的化方式是大致可以Ay的
in ways that are broadly predictable.
我的@位小朋友忽左忽右的走路方式
My friend's meandering
就好比是短期的波
represents the short-term fluctuations--
@就是天
that's weather.
基本上很yAy
It's almost impossible to predict
l知道它等河κ颤N感d趣
what'll attract his interest next,
不^我不y知道它[的
but not hard to know what the range of his meandering will be,
因槲矣闷恐它
because I'm holding him on a leash.
人不能直接^察到夂
We can't observe climate directly--
因槲所的是天
all we see is the weather--
但^好啄赆嵬扑愠龅钠骄天庾化
but the average weather, over the course of years,
揭示出一模式
reveals a pattern.
@就是一L期的
I represent that long-term trend,
@就是夂
which is climate.
把注意力放在人身上 e看狗
Keep your eye on the man, not the dog.
天夂茈yAy 就像我的@位小朋友
Weather is hard to predict, like my friend here,
但夂蚴强梢灶Ay的
but climate is predictable.
在地球漫L的v史上 夂蛟Q^好多次
Climate has changed many times in the long history of the Earth
每一次都是受某N全球性力量作用的Y果
but always in response to a global force.
F在影夂蜃化最的力量就是
The strongest force driving climate change right now
由於燃化石燃料而不嘣黾拥亩氧化碳
is the increasing CO2 from the burning of fossil fuels,
它留住了更多的太崃
which is trapping more heat from the Sun.
@些多出淼哪芰勘仨有去
All that additional energy has to go somewhere.
有些能量空馍
Some of it warms the air.
大部分的能量t被海洋吸收
Most of it ends up in the oceans.
全世界的海洋F在都在暖
All over the world, the oceans are getting warmer.
最明@的就是北冰洋
It's most obvious in the Arctic Ocean
以及它周的地
and the lands that surround it.
好吧 如果f我正在失去一些夏季的海冰
Okay, so we're losing the summer sea ice
不^那地方又是]什N人去的
in a place where hardly anyone ever goes.
我致镆P心北O有]有冰呢？
What do I care if there's no ice around the North Pole?
冰是地球最亮的自然表面
Ice is the brightest natural surface on the Earth,
V的海洋t是最暗的自然表面
and open ocean water is the darkest.
冰能把光反射回太空
Ice reflects incoming sunlight back to space.
水t吸收光而暖
Water absorbs sunlight
@更多的冰融化
and gets warmer, which melts even more ice,
更多的海洋水面暴露出
which exposes still more ocean surface
K吸收更多的光
to absorb even more sunlight.
@就是所^的正反效
This is what we call a positive feedback loop.
@是能把二氧化碳引起的嵝放大的
It's one of many natural mechanisms that magnify
S多N自然C制中的一
any warming caused by CO2 alone.
我F在是在阿拉斯加的德角
We're at Drew Point, Alaska,
@Y是北冰洋的
on the edge of the Arctic Ocean.
我出生的r候 @Y的海岸伸出去有1英里多
When I was born, the shoreline was a mile farther out,
它^去曾以每年20英尺的速度sp
and it was breaking off at a rate of about 20 feet per year.
F在……
Now...
sp的速度_到了每年50英尺
it's being eaten away at about 50 feet per year.
北冰洋正在暖
The Arctic Ocean is warming
而且暖的速度在不嘣隹
and at an increasing rate.
所以每年Y有大部分rg@Y是]有冰的
So it's ice-free during more of the year.
有更多的海岸因此暴露出
That leaves the shore here
被L暴所侵g
more exposed to erosion from storms,
@另一N力量得更大
which are also getting more powerful,
@N力量能影夂虻淖化
another effect of climate change.
阿拉斯加北部 西伯利 加拿大
The northern reaches of Alaska, Siberia and Canada
@些地方的大部分是永久性鐾
are mostly permafrost,
地面被鼋Y超^千年
ground that has been frozen year-round for millennia.
它Y面含有很多有C|
It contains lots of organic matter,
^去的淙~c涓
old leaves and roots from plants
它曾生L在登年前
that grew thousands of years ago.
由於北冰洋地^的升厮俣仍诩涌
Because the Arctic regions are warming faster
比地球上其他地^都要快
than anywhere else on Earth,
永久性鐾灵_始融化
the permafrost is thawing
鐾林械|西_始腐
and its contents are rotting,
效果就和冰箱嚯差不多
just like when you unplug the freezer.
融化的鐾玲放出二氧化碳
The thawing permafrost is releasing carbon dioxide
有甲烷 @是一N更害的的厥怏w
and methane, an even more potent greenhouse gas,
它都M入了大庵
into the atmosphere.
@世界得更
This is making things even warmer,
有一正反效的例子
another example of a positive feedback mechanism.
世界的永久性鐾又Υ嬗写罅康奶
The world's permafrost stores enough carbon
足以大庵械亩氧化碳再增加一倍
to more than double the CO2 in the atmosphere.
按照F在的速度
At the rate we're going,
全球暖很快就要F大部分了
global warming could release most of it
rg就是本世o末
by the end of the century.
人也S正在夂蛲粕弦l不w路
We might be tipping the climate past a point of no return
它走向o法A知的一面
into an unpredictable slide.
好吧 如果空 水 地
Okay, the air, the water
有其他的一切都暖了
and the land are all getting warmer,
全球暖真的l生了
so global warming is really happening.
也S@不是人的e
But maybe it's not our fault.
也S@是自然造成的
Maybe it's just nature.
也S是因樘
Maybe it's the Sun.
不 也S不是因樘
No, it's not the Sun.
我@资年硪恢痹诿芮械挠^y太
We've been monitoring the Sun very closely for decades,
而太送的能量一直都]有^
and the solar energy output hasn't changed.
有 地球F在是
What's more, the Earth is warming more at night
晚上比白天更暖
than in daytime,
冬天比夏天更暖
and more in winter than in summer.
@是符合厥倚律的
That's exactly what we expect from greenhouse warming,
c太送能量的增加
but the opposite of what increased solar output
一cPS都]有
would cause.
岩墒]有用的 F在的一切清楚表明
It's now clear beyond any reasonable doubt
人正在改夂
that we are changing the climate.
太根本就不是元
The Sun isn't the problem.
而拯救@一切的方案
But it is the solution,
人早已制淞撕芫
and we've known this for a long time,
早在比你想像中更久h的年代
much longer than you might think.
巴黎 1878年9月
Paris, September 1878.
埃菲F塔要^好多年才_始建造
The Eiffel Tower won't be built for years to come.
世博
世界上最延^非凡的景象
the world has ever seen.
自由女神像宏サ念^部
The magnificent head of the Statue of Liberty
才造好
has just been completed.
全球各地登Ъ艺股
Thousands of exhibitors from around the planet
在巴黎的66英土地上
covered 66 acres of Paris
M了他的l明ca品
with their inventions and goods.
鄣仙l明的襞葸要在好啄赆岵
Edison's first public demonstration of the light bulb
第一次向公展示
will not take place for another year.
庠O溥]有出F
There's no such thing as electrical appliances.
人不__P 按按o
People don't flick switches and press buttons.
@是一人狂R拉的世界
It's a hand-cranked, horse-drawn world.
@就是我要f到的那人
That's the guy we came to see,
那有奇怪E子的人
the one with the crazy moustache.
他是一W老 名叫W古斯丁?莫超
He's a math teacher named Augustin Mouchot.
住 @是在1878年
Remember, it's 1878.
一由煤艚y治的世界
This is a world lit mostly by gaslight.
汽要^好多年才l明
The automobile is still years away.
但莫超的l明足以^目瞪口呆
But Mouchot, here, is dazzling the crowd
那是一太能聚能O
with his solar power concentrator.
太凫段每一人
The Sun belongs to all of us!
就算它距x我1|5千f公里h
Even though it is 150 million kilometers away from us,
感受一下它那悍的威力吧
feel its awesome power!
我的l明能把太散l的免M的能量集中起
My invention concentrates the free energy of the Sun
把它D化C械\
and converts it into mechanical motion.
槿魏我环NC器提供能量
It can power any kind of machine.
它可以用戆l或者是印刷C\D
It can produce electricity or run a printing press
甚至是在崽煅u冰
or make ice on a hot day.
等著瞧吧
Et voila !
想想吧
Think of it,
既然光能D化楸K
sunlight converted into ice.
想想吧 朋友 如果我能把S富的太能利用起
You see, my friends, what wonders we can work
我能做出什N拥钠孥E
if we harness the bounteous energy of the Sun.
世界上的煤有一天用完
The world will someday run out of coal,
但x煌的太永h在那Y照耀著我
but the magnificent Sun will always be there for us.
莫超@得了@一檬澜绮┯[的金
Mouchot took home the gold medal from the fair.
但煤炭的r格下跌了
But the price of coal tumbled,
r格如此之低以至於人μ能再也]有d趣
becoming so cheap that there was no interest in solar energy.
此外 r]有人明白
Besides, no one understood, back then,
燃化石燃料的真正代r是什N
what the true cost was of burning fossil fuel.
莫超的研究M被砍掉了
Mouchot's research funding was cut off.
35年後 也就是二十世o初期
35 years later, in the early years of the 20th century,
通向另一未淼牧硪簧却箝T被打_了
another door opened to an alternative future.
它l生在埃及 尼_河岸
It happened in Egypt, on the banks of the Nile.
未淼rg旅行者住了
Memo to future time travelers...
@是一Ρ苊夂蜃化而言
this would be an excellent entry point
^佳的起c
for averting climate change.
1913年 埃及
Egypt, 1913.
@是碜悦M城的弗m克?舒曼
That's Frank Shuman of Philadelphia.
他只x^3年
He's only had three years of schooling,
但他天才的造l明能力a了@一切
but his genius for innovation more than makes up for that.
在30q以前 舒曼l明了安全玻璃
Before he was 30, Shuman had invented safety glass.
它被V泛用在汽cwC上 挽救了o档纳命
Its use in automobiles and skylights saved countless lives
也他得非常有X
and made him a very rich man,
有X 他能去追求自己真正的粝
rich enough to pursue his real passion,
太能
solar energy.
舒曼Iе一支FOK建造了
Shuman led the team that designed and built
一M太能聚能O
an array of solar energy concentrators.
它能诱羝C
It could power a steam engine.
舒曼希望利用太能
Shuman is hoping to use the Sun's power
以灌溉沙漠
to irrigate the desert
它重新G
and turn it green.
舒曼的太能l站
The official inauguration
在1913年正式
of Shuman's solar power plant, in 1913,
@是了不起的成就
was a dazzling success.
他l明了一N用的方法
He had invented a practical way to tap the Sun's energy
太能得以F工I模的用
on an industrial scale,
太能比煤更便宜
making solar energy even cheaper than coal.
英德政府
The British and German governments
o予了舒曼慷慨的助
both offered Shuman generous funding
他去造l明
to develop his invention.
@是一N理想的S富的能量碓
It was the ideal source of abundant power
尤其是在У^
in tropical regions,
那YM口煤的r格比^昂F
where imported coal was prohibitively expensive.
但舒曼有更大的粝
But Shuman was dreaming even bigger.
在o《科W美人》的一封信中
In a letter to Scientific American,
他λ的太能lSM行了算
he calculated that his solar power plants,
如果能⑺安b在一像撒哈拉沙漠那拥牡^
if deployed in an area of the Sahara Desert
只需要方A150英里的面e 就能提供
only 150 miles on a side, could supply as much power
足以世界所有工S消M的能量
as consumed by all the industries of the world.
但@一切最K]有l生
But it was not to be.
石油 @N液w化石燃料的市
The market for a liquid fossil fuel, petroleum,
S船\而蓬勃l展起
was exploding for shipping,
家庭供 汽c卡
home heating, and cars and trucks.
石油很S富 甚至比煤便宜
Oil was abundant, cheaper even than coal,
它很容易就能@得 易於加工
and much easier to get out of the ground and process.
要把煤bM一艘船 需要100人稚1周
It took 100 men a week to fuel a ship with coal,
但如果是b石油
but with oil, one man could do the job
1人稚1天就可以了
in a single day.
舒曼在沙漠中取得成功後的第2年
A year after Shuman's triumph in the desert,
第一次世界大鸨l
World War I broke out.
他的太能集崞鞅换厥 成了武器
His solar collectors were recycled into weapons.
舒曼粝胫械奶能l的文明社
Frank Shuman's dream of a solar-powered civilization
只有等到下一世o
would have to wait another century
才能@得重生的C遇
before it was reborn.
在我@世界上
There's another inexhaustible source of clean energy
有另一N取之不M的清能源
for the world.
L能本身也是由太能a生的
The winds themselves are solar-powered,
太又Lc波浪
because our star drives the winds and the waves.
c太能集崞鞑煌
Unlike solar collectors,
L能lS只需要很少的土地
wind farms take up very little land,
如果是在海 那就一c地都用不到
and none at all, if offshore,
海上的L力是最的
where the winds are strongest.
如果人能把世界上百分之一的L能利用起
If we could tap even one percent of their power,
就有充足的能源供文明社\作
we'd have enough energy to run our civilization.
而每小r落在地球上的太能量
And more solar energy falls on Earth in one hour
都超^我人社
than all the energy our civilization consumes
1年消M的能量和
in an entire year.
只要人能把很小一部分
If we could harness a tiny fraction
可用的太能cL能利用起
of the available solar and wind power,
人就有永久充足的能源供
we could supply all our energy needs forever,
而o需向大庵信欧湃魏蔚奶
and without adding any carbon to the atmosphere.
F在rq未晚
It's not too late.
未砣灾档梦^Y
There's a future worth fighting for.
楹挝夷苓@涌隙ǎ
How do I know?
我每人都是D苦Y後的存者
Every one of us comes from a long line of survivors.
如果不懂得mh境 人@物N就不存在
Our species is nothing if not adaptive.
因槲的先人W了
It was only because our ancestors learned
目光Lh r而
to think long-term, and act accordingly,
人才有今天
that we're here at all.
前有困阻 但我不能退避
We've had our backs to the wall before,
我要~向新的高度
and we came through to scale new heights.
H上 人v史上所取得的很多ゴ蟮某删
In fact, the most mythic human accomplishments of all
都是碜宰詈诎档r刻
came out of our darkest hour.
曾有@右世界
Once there was a world
6f枚核武器如箭在弦上 r刻待l
rigged with 60,000hair-triggered nuclear weapons.
@Pl生在
The combatants were
地球上最大的家之g
the two most powerful countries on Earth,
他死也要p在一起
and they were locked in a deadly embrace,
每一家都宣Q
each vowing that they would rather see
@世界玉石俱焚
everything we love destroyed
也不要不e人得到她
than submit to the will of the other.
r我才3q
When I was three years old,
有史以硗力最的人造炸
the largest man-made explosion of all time
由K引爆
was detonated by the Soviet Union.
f的恐消退 新的恐蛛S之而
That terror has subsided, to be replaced by new fears.
地球上2000最大的城市
The danger that the 2,000 largest cities on Earth
Sr有在一下午然U墟的危U
would be reduced to rubble in the space of an afternoon
但跟@比都算不上什N
is no longer one of them.
美cK之g的
The nuclear rivalry between the United States
核涓
and the Soviet Union
造了一副a品
had another by-product.
阿波_登月
The Apollo missions to the Moon were an extension
就是美Kg涓的a物
of the arms race that raged between them.
把人送上地球道
Sending people to orbit the Earth
或是送到月球 都需要大型的 可靠的
or go to the Moon requires big, reliable,
大推力火箭 而@正是
powerful rockets-- precisely the same technology
yШ^所需的科技
you need to carry a nuclear warhead
它可以w越半地球
halfway around the planet
摧的最大城市
to destroy your enemy's largest cities.
我相信@家
"I believe that this nation
一定_成@目
should commit itself to achieving the goal,
那就是在未淼氖年Y 把人送上月球
before this decade is out, of landing a man on the Moon
K他安全的返回地球
and returning him safely to the Earth."
肯尼迪y1961年的演v
President Kennedy's 1961 speech
@家d^起
electrified the nation,
Y面提到了很多人印象深刻的h景
and it contained much that was remarkably prophetic--
但在P於探月的热葜
but not a word about a scientific objective
]有一字是跟科W目有P的
for going to the Moon.
]有P於υ虑蚱鹪吹奶剿
No questions about the Moon's origin
或是Щ悠愤M行分析的想法
or the hope of bringing back samples to analyze.
阿波_c科WoP 它原本就是榱
No, the Apollo missions were conceived
展示超大的力
as a demonstration of the superior power
以及鹦g的精度
and precision of our strategic missiles.
但可笑的是
But a funny thing happened to us...
在探月的道路上
on our way to the Moon.
人回望故lr
We looked homeward...
slF了另一世界
and discovered another world--
我自己的世界
our own.
第一次 我@些地球的居民
For the first time, we inhabitants of Earth
可以後退一步 看看地球到底是什N幼
could step back and see it as it really is--
@是一不可分割的世界
one world, indivisible,
在浩瀚的宇宙中它是如此的渺小
and kind of small in the cosmic context.
不管是榱耸颤N原因 我集Y了大量的Y源
Whatever the reason we first mustered the enormous resources
投入到阿波_上
required for the Apollo program,
不管冷r期的我是如何深陷民族主x的思潮
however mired it was in Cold War nationalism
以及⑷宋淦鞯淖非
and the instruments of death,
我仍不可避免地JR到了
the inescapable recognition of the unity
地球是脆弱而不可分割的y一w
and fragility of the Earth
每一明亮l光的c都是它的M成部分
is its clear and luminous dividend,
@是阿波_的意外收
the unexpected gift of Apollo.
一致力於死亡的目
A project conceived in deadly competition
我JR了@地球共同w
made us recognize our community.
是什N拥木奕诵藿了@世界奇^？
What titan built this wonder of the world?
是菲律e伊富高省的人民
It was the Ifugao people of the Philippines,
依靠著他的p手辛勤谧
working with not much more than their hands.
在大s1f年前 我在世界各地的祖先
About 10,000 years ago, our ancestors all over the world
利用了另一N形式的夂蛲蛔
took advantage of another form of climate change,
冰河r代g歇期中出F的睾吞
the gentler climate of the intermission in the ice age--
他l明了rI
they invented agriculture.
他放了o休止的
They gave up the ceaseless wandering,
流浪 [C以及窦的生活方式
hunting and gathering that had been their way of life
@N方式曾延m了1百f年之久
for a million years or so,
他定居下 生a食物
to settle down and produce food.
他lF耕作r田
They found a way to harvest
能他比先人通^自然h境
ten to a hundred times more solar energy
@得要高出十到百倍之多的太能
than the environment naturally provided for their ancestors.
世界各地的人Dy地F了
People all over the world made the difficult transition
倪[牧文化向r耕文化的D
from nomadic cultures to agricultural ones
@是一N更有效的使用太能的方式
that used solar energy more efficiently.
@文明d盛起
It gave rise to civilization.
我就站在那些辛勤谧鞯南热说募缟
We stand on the shoulders of those who did the hard work
他槲F最基A的D
that such a fundamental transformation required.
F在 到我了
Now... it's our turn.
曾有@右世界……
Once there was a world...
如果在金星上曾有^生命 他也不有C
If life ever existed on Venus, it would have had no chance
扭D@世界走向地z的命\
to avert the hellish destiny of this world.
@N失控的厥倚是o法阻醯
This runaway greenhouse effect was unstoppable.
曾
Once...
有@右世界
there was a world...
那是我的世界
ours.
就是F在的世界
And that world is now.
]有任何科W或技g上的障K
There are no scientific or technological obstacles
阻止我保o@世界
to protecting our world
保o@世界上珍F的生命
and the precious life that it supports.
一切都取Q於
It all depends...
我真正珍惜的是什N
on what we truly value...
我能否付T於行
and if we can summon the will to act.
"槭颤N" 有人 槭颤N要x裨铝
But why, some say, the Moon?
槭颤N把它作槲的目耍
Why choose this as our goal?
他也S
And they may well ask,
我槭颤N要登上世界的最高峰？
why climb the highest mountain?
而我x窳说窃
We choose to go to the Moon...
我x窳嗽谑年鹊窃
...we choose to go to the Moon in this decade
我要做其他的事情
and do the other things,
不是因樗很容易 而是因樗很y
not because they are easy, but because they are hard.